ハア ハア
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）
だるまさんが ころんだ
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)･長野原(ながのはら)みお）
ハア ハア ハア
Red light...
Green light.
Red Light
Green Light
This is bad.
（祐子）マズい　マズい マズい
This is really bad!
もう ホームルーム
始まっちゃうよ
Homeroom's already starting!
“おばあさんを助けてました”は
このあいだ 使っちゃったし―
I was helping an old lady!
I already used that excuse last week.
“お母さんがいなかったんだよ”は
理由にならないし
"Mum wasn't around"... isn't a good reason.
ううっ どうしよう
なんて言い訳しよう
What should I do?
I need an excuse!
At least one car should go by!
せめて車１台ぐらい通ってよ
ハア ハア
（祐子）なんで
赤信号に４回も捕まるんだ
How did I get stuck at a red light four times?
結局 １時間目始まっての
登校になってしま…
First period already started a while ago-
Nichijou 40
That's such an obvious trap.
（祐子）
何？ このイージートラップ
フッ こんな古典トラップに
引っかかるわけ…
There's no way I'd fall for such an old tra-
うおっ ダブルで？
At both sides?!
What?
何？ 何？
私に対しての この遅刻制裁は
Is this my punishment for being late?
What did I do wrong?
いったい 私が何したってのよ
Even if I'm late.
遅刻だけど
Well, I can just sneak in through the back.
まっ 後ろから こっそり
入ればいいじゃないですか
そうだよ
Yeah, there's no reason to get scolded.
わざわざ正面切って
怒られることないしね
うっ くうっ
It's...
（祐子）鍵 やっぱり
掛かっちゃってますけど！
...locked, after all!
そうだ
I know!
I can sneak in through the lower door!
下のドアから
こっそり入ればいいじゃない
That's it. I'll creep in like I'm air and go into class like I'm invisible.
空気のように忍び込んで―
透けるように
授業に参加しちゃえば…
Why?!
なんでだよ！
Although, I already have an idea!
もう なんとなく分かってたよ
こんなことやるのは
御大しかいないじゃん　もう！
The only person that would do this kind of thing is the queen!
If I'm discovered sneaking in through the bottom,
ああ… 下から
こっそり入っても―
I feel like I'll get in even more trouble.
バレたら より
怒られそうな気するしね
If I'm gonna be discovered,
バレるなら いっそ
上の窓から入ってやろうか
I might as well go in through the top window!
Stained glass has been put up!
（祐子）ステンドグラスが
はめ込んであるよ！
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
待て 待て 待て 待て
Why am I running?
なに 走ってるんだ 私は
教室から逃げたって
何の解決にもならないよ
Nothing will be solved if I run away from the classroom.
とりあえず 戻ろう
I might as well go back.
Yes, the question is where it would be best to enter from.
そう 問題は どこから入れば
ベストかってこと
If I'm going to get in trouble no matter what,
なんだかんだと
最終的に怒られるんだったら―
堂々と正面突破で
玉砕(ぎょくさ)ったほうが―
brazenly charging through the front is...
...cooler!
カッコいいじゃない
Yes, the best way is...
そう ベストは―
...the eraser at the front!
正面の黒板消し！
Appearing with a huge smile while getting hit by the eraser!
黒板消しを くらいながら
満面の笑みで入場
Good morning!
おはようございまーす
And the whole class breaks out in smiles!
（祐子）そして
はじけるクラスの笑顔
What time do you think it is?
（高崎(たかさき)先生）お前　いったい
何時だと思ってるんだ？
ハア…
Man, you sure are helpless.
…ったく しょうがねえなあ
早く 席に着け
Hurry up and take your seat.
It'll work!
（祐子）イケる
That's right, Yukko!
そうよ ゆっこ
明るく 元気よく
ピエロを演じるのよ
Be a bright, energetic clown!
Now!
いざ 出陣！
Into battle!
Good morning so early in the morning!
朝も はよから
おはようございまーす　なんつって
Just kidding!
First Period is in the Language Lab.
Bubble
Oh ho ho. I'm an Invincible Alien!
（祐子）ホーホッホッホッホッ
Invincible Alien
無敵星人だ
ホーホッホッホッホッホッ
What sort of stupid thing are you doing?
何 バカなことやってんの？
小学生じゃあるまいし
It's not like you're still an elementary schooler.
The Invincible Alien is unharmed by your verbal attacks!
（祐子）無敵星人は あらゆる
攻撃を受けても無敵なのだ
Sorry about that!
（野球部員）すいませーん
大丈夫ですか？
Are you all right?
Blue Note
（阪本(さかもと)）ピョーン うるせえ！
Shut up!
Miles must be spinning in his grave!
マイルスも腰抜かすわ！
Oh, I'm sorry.
（東雲(しののめ)なの）ああっ すいません
We just got a little carried away.
つい 夢中になっちゃって
Were you listening, Sakamoto?
聴いてた？ 阪本
Of course I was listening!
（阪本）聴いてたも なにも
どんな拷問だよ これは
Are you trying to torture me!?
My ears are going to fall off!
耳が もげるわ！
We're going to do it again, so can you listen to us?
もう１回やるから
聴いてみていい？
Listen to what I have to say!
（阪本）話を聞け！
（阪本）ハア
Nagashi soumen at Tokisada Park.
Around lunchtime.
I decided to go to the nagashi soumen at a nearby park.
（安中(あんなか)）近所の公園で
流しそうめんをする
ということで―
行ってみることにした
I've only seen a nagashi soumen on TV before, so I'm really excited!
流しそうめんって
テレビでしか見たことないから―
今日は すっごく楽しみだ
I wonder... If I don't stand near the top,
やっぱり前のほうで
スタンバってないと―
そうめん流れてこないのかなあ
I won't be able to get any noodles.
I haven't eaten anything all day, so I'll sit at the front and eat a lot!
今日は何も食べてないから―
前のほうに陣取っちゃって
いっぱい食べるぞ
Slide
Nichijou 41
Here it comes!
（おばさん）まいる
（安中）えっ？
What are you doing?!
何やってんだい！
This is the first time I've seen that!
こんなの初めてだよ！
Next one's coming.
（おばさん）次 いくよ
（安中）えっ？
（安中）
あっ す… すみません あのう…
Uh, excuse me...
What is it?!
何だい！
Are you going to leave without even having a single bite?!
１口も食べずに
やめようってのかい？
Even if the law allows that...
そんなの法が許してもね
私が許さないよ！
I won't!
But... um, I don't have chopsticks.
…といいますか―
その… 箸がないんですけど
どんだけ
ずうずうしい子なんだい
What an impudent child!
Here.
ほらっ さっさと次いくよ
The next is coming right up!
All right.
（安中）あっ はい
（安中）す… すいません
Excuse me, but these chopsticks have been used...
この お手元
使ってあるんですけど
It's eco.
（おばさん）エコだよ
（安中）ええっ
Here's the next!
次いくよ
時間は待っちゃくれないよ
Time waits for no one!
No helping it... I'll just use them upside down.
しょうがない 逆で使おう
A small bit of humour.
つかの間の ユーモアだよ
The next won't be like that!
次は そうもいかないよ
I'll show you the true meaning of hell!
ホントの地獄ってやつを
見せてあげるからね
It's foolish to think there will be water forever!
いつまでも水があるなんて
平和ボケしてるんじゃないよ！
Come take it by force!
しゃにむに食らいつけってんだ
Um...
あのう…
You're a lady, aren't you?!
なでしこぶってるんじゃないよ
Why not try enjoying the raw flavour?!
少しは素材の味を
楽しんだらどうだい
Don't just stand around!
（おばさん）
グズグズしてんじゃないよ
The war isn't going to wait!
鮮度は待っちゃくれないよ
You haven't changed at all.
（江木正晴(えぎまさはる)）全然 変わってないな
Nagashi Soumen Researcher - Egi Masaharu (51)
Masaharu-san.
正晴さん…
Masaharu-san!
（おばさん）正晴さあーん！
I heard there was a nagashi soumen at the park, so I stopped by.
（江木）公園で流しそうめんを
やっていると聞いて―
ピンときたよ
（おばさん）だって あたし…
I've been doing nagashi soumen,
thinking that you would appear someday!
正晴さんが
いつか 現われると思って―
流しそうめんを…
It's been 30 years since you left on a journey in search of the ultimate nagashi soumen.
究極の流しそうめんを求め
旅に出て30年…
それは見つかったの？
Have you found it?
After eating every kind of soumen, I can no longer tell.
（江木）あらゆる
そうめんを食べてきたが―
よく分からなくなってしまった
Using our savings to travel... That money has run out.
（江木）
われわれの貯金を切り崩し―
旅をしてきたが―
そのカネも尽きてしまってな
I'm sorry.
（江木）すまんなあ
Let's wash away the nagashi soumen with water.
流しそうめんだけに
水に流してくれ
はい
Yes!
What are you looking at?!
（おばさん）何 見てんだい！
見せ物じゃないよ
This isn't a show!
（江木）
すまんが流しそうめんのように
席を外してくれないか？
TL note: Some restaurants offer nagashi-soumen "flowing noodles".
I'm sorry, but could you make like nagashi soumen and flow away?
Word Of The Day
First years, are you all here?
（テニス部顧問）
１年生　集まってるな
いいか―
Listen up.
There's the type that grows with praise and the type that grows with criticism.
褒めて伸びるタイプと
叱って伸びるタイプがいる
そこは先生の感で
判断していくぞ
I'll decide that with my instincts as a teacher.
分かったな
Got that?
Even though I grow from praise, I don't get praised at all.
NASA
（管制官）
エイト セブン
シックス ファイブ
フォー スリー
ワン
ゼロ
Launch when I say that!
What?!
Nano!
（はかせ）なの
（なの）ん？
Look at this!
見て 見て
ちょっと縛ってみました
I thought I'd try tying it up.
Does it look cool?
カッコいい？
Professor, you look a little bit like an older sister.
はかせ　ちょっとだけ
お姉さんっぽく見えますよ
Nichijou 42
Hey, hey, just how much like an older sister do I look?
はかせ
どんくらい
お姉さんっぽい？
えっ？ ええと…
Um... You look pretty older sister-like.
結構 お姉さんっぽいですよ
わああっ
じゃあ なのは？
Then what about you, Nano?
How much do you?
なのは どんなくらい？
（なの）えっ ああ いや…
Well, I might not look very older sister-like.
私は そんな
お姉さんっぽくないかもです
What a mistake!
傑作　そうか そうだったかも
I see.
That might be true.
Then, there's no helping it, so I'll clean up.
じゃあ しょうがないから
はかせが片づけます
Clean up, clean up.
（はかせ）片づけ　片づけ
（はかせ）これも
Honestly, Nano.
もう なのは…
うわっ あっ 私
まだ読んでるんですが…
I was still reading that.
なのったら
Come on, Nano.
もう　阪本も しょうがないなあ
Honestly, there's no helping Sakamoto, either.
（阪本）
んっ おい 何してんだ？
Hey, what are you doing?
You'll catch a cold.
カゼ引きますよ
What's with all this so suddenly?
（阪本）何だよ 急に
何たくらんでんだ？
What are you up to?
Honestly, Sakamoto.
もう 阪本は…
What?
（阪本）何だよ
（はかせ）カゼ引きますよ
You'll catch a cold.
（阪本）ひかねえよ
I won't!
And if you're gonna cover me, use a towel!
…っつうか 掛けるんだっだら
タオルにしろよ
Why are you using a book?
なんで本なんだよ
もう 阪本は
ああ言えば こう言う
Honestly, Sakamoto, you always try to contradict me.
I'm asking what you're doing!
だから 何してんだよ お前は
I'm going to go do laundry.
私 洗濯してきますね
あっ はかせがします
I'll do it!
It's all right, Professor.
大丈夫ですよ はかせ
もう ダイヤル回すだけなので
All that's left is to turn the dial.
There's no helping it.
もう しょうがないなあ
Then, I'll turn it.
じゃあ はかせが回します
No, that's all right. All I have to do is turn it.
あっ いや ホントに
もう 回すだけなので
だから はかせが回すから
はかせが回すの！
I told you I am going to turn it, so I am going to turn it!
Um...
えっ えーと…
Then, go ahead.
じゃあ お願いしようかな
ヘヘッ エヘッ
よいしょ
If you need help, call me.
困ったら
はかせを呼んでください
あっ はい
Okay.
（はかせ）わーい
Oh, my.
（なの）まあ
なのは しょうがないから
はかせが料理を作りますよ
You're helpless, Nano, so I'll do the cooking.
Well, I'm making it right now.
あっ いや
今 作っているところですので
Mine will taste better.
はかせのほうが
おいしいですから
Hey, come on.
（なの）いや ほら
ちょっと… 危ないですよ
Hey, hey, I'll do it.
That's dangerous!
大丈夫ですから
Don't worry.
What am I not supposed to worry about?
（なの）
いや 何が大丈夫か分から…
いや ホントに はかせ…
Professor, wai-
Hot!
（阪本）あっつ！
Hot! Hot! Hot!
熱っ 熱っ 熱っ 熱っ わあっ
Are you all right, Sakamoto-san?
（なの）大丈夫ですか？ 阪本さん
What the heck are you guys doing?!
（阪本）
何やってんだ？ お前ら！
す… すみません
I'm sorry!
阪本は しょうがないな
そんなところ歩いて
You're so helpless, Sakamoto, walking around there.
There's nothing helpless about that!
（阪本）
しょうがなくねえだろ
Stop messing around!
お前ら ふざけやがって！
Come on, Sakamoto.
まあ まあ 阪本
怒っても何もないよ
It's nothing to get mad at.
I don't understand what you're trying to imply!
（阪本）
言ってる意味が分かんねえよ！
Well, I guess I'll start over.
とりあえず
もう１回 作り直そう
あっ じゃあ はかせが作ります
Oh, then I'll make it.
Well, the other dishes will get cold, so I have to do it quickly.
いや ほかの具材が冷めちゃうので
チャッチャとやっちゃいますよ
Honestly, Nano.
もう なのは
はかせがやりますから
I'll do it.
あっ ちょっ
はかせ 危ないですよ
Hey, Professor! That's dangerous!
The eggs will fall!
卵 落ちちゃいますよ
（はかせ）大丈夫ですから
It's all right.
Hey, watch out!
（阪本）おい 危ないぞ
It's all right.
（はかせ）大丈夫ですから
You're so helpless.
（はかせ）もう しょうがないな
No, you are!
（阪本）お前だ お前
Hey, Girl, what's up with the kid today?
おい 娘　どうしたんだ
今日のガキは
I think she wants to act like an older sister.
多分 お姉さんっぽいことを
したいんだと
Since I am an older sister.
お姉さんですから
Damn.
おい ガキ
Hey, kid.
何？
What?
Did you know that older sisters don't eat snacks?
（阪本）お姉さんは
お菓子を食べないって知ってたか？
ジャーン
Tada!
I was actually the Professor!
実は 本当のはかせでした
（阪本）
アッハハハハ
アハッ アハッ アハハハハ
ウソつけ
Liar.
No way!
ウソーッ
River Fishing
うおっ 結構デカい
Hey, this is pretty large.
Whoa!
うわあ 長靴だ
It was a boot.
あっ 今度こそ きたぞ
This time, I really got something!
What!?
ぬわっ やかんだ
It's a kettle!
In a way, isn't this better than fish?
ある意味
魚よりすごくないか？ これ
ハア
If I knew these kinds of things were going to happen,
こんな面白いこと起こるなら
誰かを誘ってくるべきだった
I would have brought someone along.
Oh, well.
出直すか
Trendy things.
粋なもの
Eating sushi with your hands.
素手で すし
チキショウ
Crap!
I don't want to do my homework!
宿題したくね
Nichijou 43
Why do we even have to do homework in the first place?
そもそも 宿題って―
なんで やんなきゃなんないんだ？
Well, since my marks aren't good, I have to do it.
まあ 確かに成績が悪いから
やんなきゃいけないんだけど―
But I'm equipped with enough skill to avoid failing marks,
赤点は なんとか回避できる
能力は備わってるから―
so I won't be held back.
進級は大丈夫　…だと思う
I think.
And after I graduate, I don't want to go to university to study more.
そして 卒業して―
大学まで行って
勉強はしたくないし
就職？
Should I work?
But I heard on TV that it's difficult to find employment.
でも このあいだ テレビで
就職難っつってたし―
Without a degree, it might be difficult.
学歴がないと厳しいのかな？
High School
高校
College.
大学
Employment.
就職
You can't get through without a university entrance exam.
避けては通れぬ大学受験
But right now, I don't want to study!
でも！
とにかく勉強したくねえ！
大体 今やってる勉強が
将来 何の役に立つってえの？
Anyway, how will what I'm studying now help me in the future?!
いや… ちょっと待て
Wait a minute.
What's my dream for the future?
将来の夢って… 何だ？
My Dream for the Future, by Aioi Yukko.
（祐子）将来の夢　相生祐子
私の将来の夢は
エリマキトカゲになることです
My dream for the future is to be a frill-necked lizard.
Frill-necked.
I don't want to study!
（祐子）勉強したくねえ
I don't want to study, and I don't want to be a frill-necked lizard!
勉強したくねえし―
エリマキトカゲには
なりたくねえ！
No, wait a minute.
いや 待てよ
If I become a frill-necked lizard, I might be released from this burden.
逆にエリマキトカゲに
なっちゃえば―
この悩みから
解放されるかもしれないなあ
…でも どうせなるなら―
But I might as well become a living national treasure and be spoiled.
人間国宝とかになって
ちやほやされるのもいいなあ
Some
Clay-like
Thing
あ？ そういや 人間国宝って
毎月いくらもらえるんだ？
Some
Clay-like
Thing
By the way, I wonder how much a living national treasure gets paid a month.
Payment
そもそも 人間国宝って
どうやってなるんだ？
And how do you become a living national treasure in the first place?
そもそも 人間国宝って何だ？
And more importantly, what is a living national treasure?
No, no, no.
いや いや いや
I should think more realistically.
もっと 現実的に考えよう
What I want to be... want to be... want to be...
私がなりたいもの…
なりたいもの…
It's no good.
ダメだ　見当がつかない
I can't come up with anything.
Well, I'm still a first year high schooler.
いや まだ高１だし
I have three years to think about it.
３年間 考える時間あるし
それでも 見つからなかったら…
If I can't figure it out by then...
University!
大学… 受験
Exams!
In other words...
すなわち…
I don't want to study!
勉強したくねえ
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
いや いや いや いや
Getting depressed about it won't help.
落ち込んでもしょうがない
I should worry after I think of what I want to be!
なりたいもので考えるから
悩むんだ
I'll try thinking of something I'd like to do!
ここはひとつ―
やりたいことを
考えてみようじゃないか！
Something I'd like to do... like to do, huh?
やりたいこと…
やりたいことねえ
いや うーん
おおっ！ うんん！
Mum!
（祐子）お母さん！
（祐子の母）らっしゃ！
（祐子）どあっ
Your pounding is obnoxious!
ドカドカ ドカドカ うるさいよ
What time do you think it is?!
何時だと思ってんの！
（祐子）まっ 難しいことは
よく分かんないし
Well, I don't really understand hard things.
For now, how about I do my homework?
とりあえず 宿題しとくか
Crap!
チキショウ
I don't want to do my homework!
宿題したくねえ
Yo! It's me, the origami frill-necked lizard!
（エリマキトカゲ）
おいら エリマキトカゲ
折り紙で作んの
すげえ難しいんだ
おいらが完成するまでに―
It's really difficult to make me in origami!
折り紙２枚は
ゴミ箱行きになっちゃうかもな
To make me, you're going to need two pieces of paper!
Next time, Nichijou 11.
次回の「日常」は第11話
楽しみにしてくれよ
Narration:     Nozawa Masako
Be prepared for it!